Guide to the E.L. McGlashan Collection of Documents Concerning Slavery in the United States
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
E. L. McGlashan collection of documents concerning slavery in the United States
1770-1863
GEN MSS 555
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
This collection of 46 documents consists of manuscript bills of sale, receipts, estate appraisals, deeds of gift, manumission statements, promissory notes, and other papers documenting slave ownership and the slave trade in the United States between 1770 and 1863. The bulk of the material documents slavery in North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, Georgia, Kentucky and Alabama. There are also legal documents recording slavery transactions in Maine, Tennessee, Pennsylvania, and Louisiana.
McGlashan, E. L. (Everitt Lynn), 1911-1978
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Scott McGlashan to the Gilder Lehrman Center of Yale University. Gift of the Gilder Lehrman Center of Yale University, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
E. L. MCGLASHAN (1911-1978)
Everitt Lynn McGlashan was born in Perth, New York in 1911. A collector of Americana, his focus was on antiquarian books, archives, and ephemera documenting the American South and West. Most of the documents in McGlashan's collection of slavery material were purchased from secondhand bookstores in the nineteen sixties during family vacations in Richmond, Atlanta, New Orleans and other southern cities. McGlashan died in North Tarrytown, New York in 1978.
Scope and Contents
The E. L. McGlashan Collection of Papers Concerning Slavery in the United States consists of bills of sale, receipts, estate records, and other material documenting slave ownership and the slave trade in the United States. The papers span the dates 1770-1862, and predominantly document transactions in North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, Georgia, Kentucky, and Alabama. There are also records which document legal actions involving slaves in Maine, Tennessee, Pennsylvania, and Louisiana.
Series I. Bills of Sale is arranged chronologically and consists of 11 documents. The folder titles consist of transcribed information, and include the names of sellers, buyers, and slaves, as well as the dates of sales. The jurisdiction of sales has been transcribed when recorded. These documents also typically include the amount for which the slaves were sold; a witness statement; and the date of the sale's recording at the country clerk's office or other official registry. Some sales include description of the skills, age, physical condition and family relationships of the slaves. In many cases, annotations on the verso record subsequent transactions. Some records also provide information about the seller. The 1840 bill of sale for slaves sold by Antoine Lacour of Iberville Parish, Louisiana (folder 11) notes that the Lacour is a "free man of color."
Series II. Receipts is arranged chronologically and consists of 11 documents. The receipts usually include information about the sale, including the amount of money paid, the name of the slave, and the date of the sale. Some receipts also include a description of the physical condition and family relationships of the slaves being sold. Several of the receipts in this collection are recorded on preprinted forms completed in manuscript (folders 13, 14, 17, 18).
Series III. Estate Records is arranged chronologically and consists of property appraisals and inventories of the estates of deceased individuals in various Alabama counties between 1843 and 1860. Inventories typically list the names of slaves and their valuation, as well as descriptions and valuation amounts for other personal property owned by the deceased. The records are annotated with witness statements, attestations, and often bear notes regarding the administration of the estate and the final division of property.
Series IV. Other Documents is arranged chronologically and consists of 16 manuscript and printed items related to slavery in the United States. The series includes deeds gifting slaves to relatives (folders 32, 36, 39, 41, 44), contracts for hiring out slave labor (folders 33, 35), and manumission statements, including one document that records the registering of three mulatto boys and their slave mother shortly after Pennsylvania's 1780 Gradual Abolition of Slavery Act (folder 31).
Documents in this collection were already numbered using a three character alphanumeric code when the materials were acquired by the Beinecke Library in 2005. The Gilder Lehrman Center used these codes in citations for items from this collection that were digitized for the Center's workshop "Sound as a Dollar: The Paperwork of Chattel Slavery." The codes have been retained in this finding aid and are listed in parentheses following the folder description.
African Americans -- History -- To 1863; Slave trade -- United States; Slaveholders -- United States; Slavery -- United States; Slaves -- Emancipation -- United States; Slaves -- United States; Conveyances; Estate inventories; Receipts (financial records); Slaveholders -- United States; McGlashan, E. L. (Everitt Lynn), 1911-1978
- Bills of Sale, 1789-1840; Series I; 0.11; (1/4 box)
  - Gray, Stevens of Bertie County, North Carolina to Edward Turner, "one Negro woman named Priss" (C25), 1789 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rhodes, John of Bertie County, North Carolina to Joshua Davis, [Glasgow?] County, "Negro man named Jacob" (C30), 1793 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ferrell, Jephthah of Wake County, North Carolina to Patrick Terrell, "Negro boy named Jack about seventeen years old" (C1), 1793 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Warrin, Pleasant F. of Halifax County, Virginia to Mary Fulcher of Person County, North Carolina, "Negro boy about four years old named Gilbred" (C29), 1798 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Boughton, Thomas of Essex County, [Virginia?] to Joseph Janey, "one Negroe woman named Halse" (H3), 1806 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Verso notations record sale of Halse by Janey six days later to Abraham Shepherd and Shepherd's sale to John McDonogh and Shepherd Brown in New Orleans on 1708 Feb 10
  - Jones, William and Nathaniel Howcott, Chowan County, North Carolina, "four Negroes, names as follows Rachel, Biner, Steaven, and Hannah" (H25), 1807 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Satterfield, David of Person County, North Carolina to Jesse Lunsford, "a certain Negro boy by the name of Sam of a yellow complexion about ten years old" (C28), 1817 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Haley, James H. of Wake County, North Carolina to Burrell Perry, "a certain Negro named Anthony about fifteen years of age" (C7), 1821 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hill, Benjamin of [P. County?] to Williamson Harpe, "one Negro girl named Becky, five years old" (C9), 1822 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hanlin, William of Hickman County, Tennessee to Lawson H. Nunnely, "a certain Negro boy named Andy about thirteen years of age" (H84), 1829 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lacour, Antoine of Iberville Parish, Louisiana to Macques Molaison Jr. of West Baton Rouge Parish, Louisiana, "two slaves... Peter, a Negro man aged thirty years, and Paul, a Negro man also aged thirty years" (C39), 1840 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Receipts, 1846-1862; Series II; 0.1; (1/4 box)
  - Davis, John. Receipt for "two Negroes, Jacob and Sam" from Thomas H. Anderson (H77), 1846 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Perry, Willie. Receipt for "purchase of one Negro slave named Zena," sold to E. H. Simmons. Richmond, [Virginia] (C4), 1847 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miller, D. M. Receipt for "purchase of Negro slave named Moses," sold to E. H. Simmons. Richmond, [Virginia] (C23), 1847 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Bloodgood?], John. Receipt for "Madison and his wife Nancy, and two children, also Patty and an old woman... also Stephen [Hitchow?], his wife Hester," sold to Joseph Lundry. Montgomery, [Alabama] (H75), 1848 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sumner, Benjamin. Receipt for purchase of "one Negroe slave named Priscilla aged about twenty-two years," sold to E. H. Simmons. Lincoln County, North Carolina (C8), 1849 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Campbell, B. M. & W. L. Receipt for sale of "four Negro slaves named Betsy and her three children... Rachel, Clea, and Eliza" to E. H. Simmons. Baltimore, [Maryland] (C2), 1851 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hall, William. W. Receipt for "purchase of a Negro slave named Mary and her child Louisianna," sold to Charles H. Shield. Norfolk, [Virginia] (H61), 1853 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Harrison, C. A. Receipt for sale of "boy, Dick, aged about seven years," sold to W. W. Holden. Wake County, North Carolina (C6), 1857 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Spins, W. Receipt for sale of "a Negro man named Peter," sold to E. H. Simmons. Hamburg (C3), 1857 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Marlen, W. L. Receipts for two slaves sold to John H. Newton. Jackson County, Georgia (H26, H27), 1862 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
- Estate Records, 1843-1860; Series III; 0.1; (1/4 box)
  - Bethen, Hugh. Monroe County, Alabama (H79), 1843 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Young, Hugh. Wilcox County, Alabama (H81), 1844 Jan 24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sellers, Samuel. Wilcox County, Alabama (H82), 1852 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Evans Law, John Alex. Wilcox County, Alabama (H76), 1859 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Burton, Ephraim T. Greene County, Alabama (C32, C33), 1860 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Haddox, Catherine. Wilcox County, Alabama (H80), 1860 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Other Documents, 1770-1863; Series IV; 0.11; (1/4 box); 0.11' (1/4 box)
  - Martin, Jacob. Manumission document for a "Negro manservant named Boston," [Biddeford, Maine?] (M12), 1770 Aug 17 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Boyd, William of Lancaster, Pennsylvania. Record of registration for three mulatto children and their mother (C22), 1789 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dargan, Ann. Deed of gift and sale for "the moiety of the Negro man slave named Virginia" to nephew William Moon, Bertie County, North Carolina (C26), 1802 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Nicohols, Zachariah. Contract for "the hire of a negro Pearse for the ensuing year" (C21), 1808 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Henry Gorin acting for William W. Whitaker. Execution against property form, issued against [Lewith Lofland, Iavano Cromwell, Charles Lofland, and Lamuel Hill?]. Logan County, Kentucky (H16), 1822 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Verso bears notations for carrying out payment of debt, including sale of slaves
  - Brooks, R. S. and R. J. [Vallant?]. Contract for "the hire [of] Negro boy Wright," from William Bibb, [Huntsville, Alabama] (C35), 1827 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Harward, John. Deed of gift for "one Negro girl by the name of Marget" to his son, John Harward, Wake County, North Carolina (C5), 1830 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bonan, John and James Petty. Promissory note for purchase of "Negro man name[d] Ben" (C10), 1832 Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clagett, Richard. "Public Sale of Negroes," Potters Mart, Charleston, South Carolina, printed broadside (C38), 1833 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - [Gains, Janus?] of Randolph County, North Carolina. Deed of gift for "one Negro man named Isham about twenty years old, one Negro woman named Carolina about twenty-five years old, and another Negro woman named Uma and her child Alfred," to his daughter, Julia E. [Armstead?] of Wilcox County, Alabama (H78), 1835 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Inventory and sale of 1/6 Negro man, Moses, and 1/6 part of Negro woman, [Pheriley?]... Richard C. Fulford's estate," manuscript copy (C37), 1837 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Walker, Moses of Person County, North Carolina. Deed of gift for "one Negro man Ferryman, one boy Frank," to his son, Alexander Walker of Halifax County, Virginia (C27), 1847 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Burwell, Cornelius and T. J. Execution against property form, issued against estate of H. W. Wells and Thomas R. Wells. Logan County, Kentucky (H17), 1859 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Attached document dated 1859 May 13 records transfer of "a Negro boy" to sheriff in payment of debt
  - [Ramsey?], Joseph B. Note relating to capture of escaped slave, Augusta, [Georgia] (C36), 1859 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Brown, Burwell of Wake County, North Carolina. Deed of gift for "the following slaves Caroline, Henry, Mary, Alek, William," to his son-in-law, Richard J. Holt (C11), 1861 Nov 14 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Harris, James M. for S. Tinsley. Tax certificate, printed form completed in manuscript, Bedford County, [Virginia] (C12), 1860 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Wells, Irby S. Duplicate receipt related to claim for compensation against the Confederate government for loss of a slave employed in military fortifications, Columbia, South Carolina (C16), 1863 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 46)